Jessica Godwin

CSDE

University of Washington Box 353412 Seattle, WA 98195-3412 jlg0003@uw.edu

https://jlgodwin.github.io/ +1(256)348-7799 Raitt Hall 218C

Current Position

Center for Studies in Demography & Ecology (CSDE), University of Washington

Supervisors: Sara Curran (scurran@uw.edu), Matt Dunbar (mddunbar@uw.edu)

Statistical Demographer & Training Director

September 2021-Present

Perform statistical and demographic consulting for faculty affiliates of CSDE and graduate researchers campus-wide. Teach professional development seminar for CSDE Graduate Trainees in the Graduate Certificate Program in Demographic Methods. Continue to develop and support the Population Dynamics Lab, an online forum for the publication of advancements in demographic and population research committed to reproducibility and accessibility of scientific research.

Education

University of Washington

Ph.D. in Statistics, Demographic Methods

July 2021

Research advisor: Jon Wakefield

Dissertation: Spatiotemporal estimation of period child mortality in a low and middle income

countries context

Auburn University

M.S. in Statistics August 2013

Research advisor: Nedret Billor

Thesis: The group lasso for functional logistic regression

B.S. in Actuarial Science, Summa Cum Laude

May 2011

Publications

Glass, DJ, **Godwin J**, Bez, E, Corley, MK, Valeggia, CR and Martin, MA (2024). "Longitudinal analysis of cortisol changes during pubertal development in indigenous Qom girls". *American Journal of Human Biology*, p.e24133.

Jones-Smith JC, Knox MA, Chakrabarti S, Wallace J, Walkinshaw L, Mooney SJ, **Godwin J**, Arterburn DE, Eavey J, Chan N, Saelens, BE (2024). "Sweetened Beverage Tax Implementation and Change in Body Mass Index Among Children in Seattle". *JAMA Network Open* 7(5):e2413644. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.13644

Saba SK, **Godwin J**, Hong SH, Pan T, Chang Y, Brindle E, & Herrenkohl TI (2023). "Associations between childhood maltreatment and physiological dysregulation in adulthood: methodological decisions and implications". *Child Abuse & Neglect* 144, 106369.

Godwin J, Wakefield J (2021) "Space-time modeling of child mortality at the Admin-2 level in a low and middle income countries context". *Statistics in Medicine*, 1-46.

Li Z, Hsiao Y, **Godwin J**, Martin BD, Wakefield J, Clark SJ (2019) "Changes in the spatial distribution of under-five mortality rate: Small-area analysis of 122 DHS surveys in 262 subregions of 35 countries in Africa". *PloS One* 14(1).

Wakefield J, Fuglstad GA, Riebler A, **Godwin J**, Wilson K, Clark SJ (2018) "Estimating underfive mortality in space and time in a developing world context". Statistical Methods in Medical Research 28(9), 2614-2634.

Sharrow DJ, **Godwin J**, He Y, Clark SJ, Raftery AE (2018) "Probablistic Population Projections for Countries with Genralized HIV/AIDS Epidemics". *Population Studies* 72(1), 1-15.

Godwin J, Raftery AE (2017). "Bayesian Projections of Life Expectancy Accounting for the HIV/AIDS Epidemic". *Demographic Research* 37, 1549-1610.

Wakefield J, Simpson D, **Godwin J** (2016). "Comment: Getting into Space with a Weight Problem". *Journal of the American Statistical Association* 111(515), 1111-1118.

Billor N, **Godwin J** (2015). "Variable Selection for Functional Logistic Regression in fMRI Data Anaylsis". *Turkiye Klinikleri Journal of Biostatistics* 7(1).

Book Chapters

Marquez, N, **Godwin J**, & Curran, S (2023). VIRAL INFECTIONS, RACE, AND AGE IN THE UNITED STATES. In DA Swanson & RR Verdugo, *Socio-Demographic Perspectives on the COVID-19 Pandemic* (pp. 67–81). Information Age Publishing.

Conference Presentations

Population Association of America

April 2023

Oral presentation: Counting Deaths and Exposures for Period Child Mortality Measures in the DHS

Population Association of America

April 2019

Oral presentation: Small Area Estimation of Child Mortality at Admin-2 Level

Population Association of America

April 2017

Oral presentation: Probabilistic Projections of Mortality in Countries with Generalized HIV Epidemics for Use in Total Population Projection

Population Association of America

April 2016

Joint Statistical Meetings

August 2015

Oral presentation: Bayesian Projections of Life Expectancy Accounting for HIV Prevalence for All Countries in the World

Joint Statistical Meetings Southern Regional Council on Statistics

August 2013

June 2013

Poster presentation: The Group Lasso for Functional Logistic Regression

Research Experience

University of Washington

Project Lead, CSDE & PHI Applied Research Fellowship Program Summer 2021-2024

Scope summer project for stakeholders at King County to be completed by team of 5 student fellows (3 graduate, 2 undergraduate). Advise and direct research into changes and trends in household composition by size and ownership status and housing stock and its vulnerabilities and development of online visualization tool for spatiotemporal results.

Supervisors: Sara Curran (scurran@uw.edu), Arti Shah (artishah@uw.edu)

Data Scientist, eScience Data Science for the Social Good

Summer 2022

Co-lead a team of 4 student fellows (2 undergraduate, 2 graduate) in the solving the computational and statistical problem of aggregating individual level administrative data into households in order to study intergenerational poverty in Washington state.

Supervisors: Jennie Romich (romich@uw.edu), Anissa Tanweer (tanweer@uw.edu)

Research Assistant

July 2015-July 2017

Bayesian spatiotemporal estimation of under-five mortality.

Advisor: Jon Wakefield (jonno@uw.edu)

Research Assistant

June 2014-July 2015

Bayesian hierarchical modeling of life expectancy in the presence of HIV.

Advisor: Adrian Raftery (raftery@uw.edu)

Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research

Pre-doctoral Researcher

Winter 2019-Spring 2019

Lab of Digital and Computational Demography. Subnational estimation of adolescent and young adult mortality in low and middle income countries.

Supervisor: Emilio Zagheni (zagheni@demogr.mpg.de)

Teaching Experience

Note: (UG) denotes undergraduate course, and (G) denotes graduate course.

University of Washington

Research Methods in Demography (G) Instructor, SOC/CSSS/CSDE 533	Winter 2024
Responsible Conduct of Research (G) Instructor, CSDE 502	Spring 2022-2024
Spatial Statistics (G) TA, STAT 554	Winter 2021
Survey Statistics (G) TA, STAT 529	Spring 2020, 2018
Review of Mathematics for Social Scientists (G) Instructor, CSSS 505	Winter 2020, 2018
Statistical Programming in R and SAS Instructor, STAT 302	Autumn 2019
Review of Mathematics, R, and STATA (G) Instructor, CSSS Math Camp	Sept. 2016-2021
Intro to Statistics for Social Scientists (G) TA, SOC 504	Autumn 2018
Intro to Statistics for Social Scientists (UG) TA, STAT 221 Autumn	2013-Spring 2014

Auburn University

Introduction to Statistics and R (UG) Instructor, STAT 2510

Fall 2011-Spring 2013

Previous Professional Experience

Sparta, Inc.

Systems Analyst

Summer 2011, 2012

Model and Simulation team. Use simulation software and statistical methods to build a model of a cancer treatment facility to design an efficient hospital floor plan and optimize resource levels in order to minimize patient time in system.

Supervisor: Jim Walsh (james.walsh@parsons.com)

Honors and Awards

University of Washington

CSDE Shanahan Fellow	2020
CSSS Travel Award	Spring 2017
CSDE Big Data to Knowledge Fellowship	2017
CSDE Travel Award	Spring 2016

Auburn University

Master's Thesis Award

October 2014

Awarded to up to three Master's theses per year in Mathematics, Physical Sciences and Engineering

COSAM Travel Award

Summer 2013

Applied, was accepted and provided with funding to attend

John and Rosemary Brown Scholarship

Fall 2009-Spring 2010

Given to one male and one female junior and senior majoring in Mathematics

Merit Scholarship
Spirt of Auburn Presidential Scholarship

2007–2011

2007-2011

Other

Undergraduate Workshop: Object Data Analysis, SAMSI	Spring 2011
Society of Actuaries P Exam Passed	May 2010
Society of Actuaries FM Exam Passed	November 2009

Service

Reviewer

PLoS One, Demographic Research, Demography, Biometrics Journal, Journal of the American Statistical Association

Center for Studies in Demography & Ecology, University of Washington

Population Dynamics Lab

2020-Present

Development and Editor of The Denominator and The Download

Department of Statistics, University of Washington

SBUG 2017–2020

Founder and member of leadership of an organization in UW's Statistics and Biostatistics departments to create community for and provide extra support and resources to women and nonbinary students.

Diversity Committee

January 2017-December 2018

Graduate Student Representative to Faculty

May 2015-May 2017

Plan all recruitment activities for prospective Ph.D. students, plan all orientation activities for incoming Ph.D./M.S., attend faculty meetings.

Student Representative, ASA

May 2015-August 2017

Liaison between students and the officers of the Puget Sound Chapter of the American Statistical Association

Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Auburn University

Science Olympiad 2011–2013

Event judge middle school Science Olympiad meet held yearly at Auburn University.

Computing

Proficient in: R, SAS, Stata, Excel, C, Minitab, SPSS, ExtendSim8